Okay, our basic array implementation of stacks had the defect where
앞에서 다룬 기본적인 배열 기반의 스택 구현은
we required clients to provide the maximum capacity of the stack ahead of time.
사용자가 사전에 스택의 최대 용량(maximum capacity)을 제공해야 하는 약점이 있었습니다.
Now we're going to look at a technique for resolving that problem.
이제 그 문제를 해결할 기법을 살펴봅시다.
How do we, we do not implementing the API?
용량을 명시하지 않고 API를 구현할 방법은 뭘까요?
The API says we should just be able to create a stack and
스택 API는 스택을 만들 수 있고,
it should be able to grow and shrink to any size.
임의의 크기로 키우고 줄일 수 있어야 합니다.
So how are we going to grow and shrink the array?
어떻게 하면 배열을 키우고 줄일 수 있을까요?
Well, first thing you might think of is, when the client pushes a new item onto
쉽게 생각해 볼 수 있는 방법은 사용자가 새 아이템을 스택에 넣을 때
the stack, increase the size of the array by 1, and when it pops,
배열의 크기를 1만큼 키우고, 뺄 때
decrease the size of the array by 1.
1만큼 줄이는 겁니다.
That's easy to code up, but
코드 짜기 쉽겠죠. 하지만
not worth it, because it's much too expensive to do that.
그걸 하는데 드는 비용을 고려하면 가치가 있진 않습니다.
The reason is that you have to create a new array, size one bigger, and
그 연산을 하기 위해서는 크기가 1 커진 새로운 배열을 만들고
copy all the items to that new array.
새 배열에 기존 배열의 아이템들을 복사해야 하기 때문입니다.
So, inserting the first N items would take time proportional,
따라서 처음 N 개의 아이템을 삽입하는 시간은 N(N-1)에 비례합니다.
if the stack's of size N-1, it's going to take time N, N-2, time N-1.
왜냐면 꽉찬 스택의 용량이 N-1일 때 새 아이템을 삽입하는 시간은 N에 비례하기 때문입니다.
So first N items would take the sum of the first N integers,
즉, 처음 N 개의 아이템의 삽입은 1부터 N까지의 정수의 합이므로
which we know is about N squared over 2.
N(N-1)/2에서 대략 (N^2)/2가 됩니다.
Quadratic time to insert N items into a stack,
스택에 N 개의 아이템을 삽입하는 데 이차식의 수행 시간(quadratic time)이 걸린다는 건,
that kind of performance is unacceptable for
지금까지 몇 번에 걸쳐서 보아왔듯이,
large problems, as we've seen, as we will see many times.
큰 문제에서는 이와 같은 성능을 받아들일 수 없습니다.
So the challenge is to do the resizing, but
따라서 우리가 풀 과제는 '리사이징을 해야 하긴 하는데,
somehow ensure that it happens infrequently.
어느 정도 덜 빈번하게 했으면 좋겠다'는 겁니다.
So the well-known technique for doing that,
따라서 이를 하기 위한 잘 알려진 방법은
called repeated doubling, is to, when the array fills up,
반복 배증(repeated doubling)이라 하는데요. 배열이 꽉 차면
create a new array of twice the size and copy all the items over.
새 배열의 크기를 2'배'로 '증'가시키고 기존 아이템을 복사하는 겁니다.
Then we don't create new arrays all that often.
이러면 새 배열을 그리 자주 생성하진 않겠죠.
So here's an implementation of that.
여기 구현이 있습니다.
We start with an array of size 1.
시작할 때는 배열의 크기를 1로 하고요.
If we have a full stack, which we know by testing N,
스택이 꽉 차면 - 이건 N을 검사해보면 알겠죠.
which is the number of items in the stack versus the array length, then
N이 스택 내에 아이템의 숫자이니, 이 값과 배열의 길이를 비교하는 겁니다. -
we just resize the array into one of twice the length before inserting the item.
이제 배열의 크기를 1에서 2로 2배 늘리고 아이템을 삽입합니다.
And how do we resize to a new capacity?
배열의 크기를 새로운 용량으로 바꾸는 건 어떻게 할까요?
We create a new array of that capacity and just go ahead and copy our
그 용량에 맞는 새 배열을 생성하고, 그대로 현 스택의 배열의
current stack into the first half of that and then return it.
모든 아이템을 복사해온 뒤, 스택 클래스가 가진 배열 참조 s를 업데이트 합니다.
And that will reset our instance variable,
이렇게 되면 스택의 인스턴스 변수 s가
which is our stack, to this new, bigger array.
새로운 더 큰 배열을 가리키게 됩니다.
[COUGH] So, the idea and the consequence of this is,
지금까지 살펴본 내용을 바탕으로 결론을 내보죠.
if you insert N items into an array, into a stack with this array representation,
배열 표현을 활용한 스택에 N 개의 아이템을 배열에 삽입하면,
the time will be proportional to N, not N squared.
이제 그 실행 시간은 N^2이 아니라 N에 비례하게 됩니다.
And the reason is that you only create a new array every time it doubles.
그 이유는 새 배열의 용량을 2배씩 늘리게 되는데,
But by the time that it doubles, you've inserted that many items into the stack.
용량이 2배 늘어날 때마다, 스택에 더 많은 아이템을 (배열 리사이징 없이) 삽입 가능합니다.
So on average, it's like adding a cost of one to each operation.
따라서 평균적으로, 각 연산의 비용에 1이 더해지게 되므로
So if you just calculate the cost of inserting the first N items,
N 개의 아이템을 삽입하는 비용을 계산하면
you're going to have instead of the sum of the integers from to 1 to N,
1부터 N까지의 정수의 합 대신에
you're going to have the sum of the powers of 2 from 1 to N.
배열 접근 비용인 N에다가, '2의 지수승 2^i를 i=1부터 2^i가 N을 초과하기 직전까지의 합'을 더한 값이 되는데
And that'll give a total cost of about 3N.
그때 가능한 최대 i는 log_2 N이고, 등비수열의 합 공식에 따라 2(2^(log_2 N) - 1)/(2-1) = 2N-2이니 총 비용은 대략 3N이 됩니다.
So that's, in array accesses for the copy, there's two array accesses.
정리하면, 아이템을 한 번 넣을 때마다 copy로 인해 배열 접근이 한 번 있고, 반복 배증으로 인해 평균적으로 2 번 배열을 접근하므로
So to insert N items, it's about three array accesses.
N개의 아이템의 삽입을 위해서 각 아이템 삽입 때마다 대략 3번의 배열 접근이 발생합니다.
This plot is another way of looking at it,
아래 그림은 지금까지의 논의를 다르게 보여주는데요.
which is the number of array accesses taken as you implement push operations.
push 연산을 구현했을 때 배열 접근의 수를 나타낸 겁니다.
Every time you hit a power of 2, you take that many array accesses, but in a sense,
배열이 꽉 찰 때, 즉 2^n번째 원소를 삽입할 때, 그만큼 많은 배열 접근을 필요로 하지만, 어떤 측면에서
you've already paid for them by putting those items on the stack.
즉, 스택에 아이템을 넣는 전체 과정에서 사실은 이미 비용을 지불했다고 볼 수 있습니다.
So that's called amortized analysis,
이를 분할상환분석(amortized analysis)이라 합니다.
where we consider the total cost averaged over all operations.
여기서는 '모든 연산에 대한 비용'의 평균을 냅니다.
And this is a fine example and useful example,
방금 본 것은 스택 구현의 효율성을 알기 위한
of amortized analysis to get efficiency in a stack implementation.
분할상환분석의 좋은, 유용한 에시입니다.
Now we have, what about the pop, we have to think about how to shrink the array.
이제 pop 연산은 어떨까요? 이 때는 배열을 줄이는 걸 고민해야 합니다.
So, you might think, well, we doubled it when it was full,
쉽게 생각했겠지만 꽉 찼을 때 배증했으므로
why don't we cut it in half when it gets to be half full?
pop으로 인해 아이템의 수가 용량의 절반이 되었을 때 용량을 절반으로 줄이면 어떨까요?
We don't want the array to get too empty.
배열이 너무 비는 걸 원하진 않으니까요.
Well, that one doesn't exactly work because of a phenomenon called thrashing.
이 방법은 스래싱(thrashing)이라 불리는 현상으로 인해 제대로 동작하지 않습니다.
If the client happens to do push-pop-push-pop alternating when
사용자가 배열이 꽉 찼을 때 push-pop-push-pop을 교대로 반복했다고 합시다.
the array is full, then it's going to be doubling, having, doubling,
그러면 2배, 1/2배, 2배, 1/2배,
having, doubling, having.
2배, 1/2배를 반복하며
Creating new arrays on every operation.
매 연산마다 새로운 배열을 만드려고 하겠죠.
Take time proportional to N for every operation, and
각 연산은 N에 비례하는 시간이 걸리므로
therefore quadratic time for everything.
전체 시간은 이차식의 실행 시간을 가집니다.
So I don't want to do that.
이런 결과는 원하지 않습니다.
The efficient solution is to
효율적인 해법은
wait until the array gets one-quarter full before you have it.
배열이 용량의 1/4배만큼만 찼을 경우에 pop이 실행되면 용량을 줄이는 것입니다.
And that's very easy to implement.
매우 구현하기 쉽죠.
We can just test if the array is one quarter full, if it is,
배열이 용량의 1/4배만큼 찼다면,
we resize it to half full.
배열의 용량을 절반으로 줄입니다.
And so then at that point, it's half full, and
절반으로 줄어든 그 시점에서
it can either grow by adding stuff or shrink by subtracting stuff.
여러 아이템을 추가해서 늘리거나 제거해서 줄일 수 있습니다.
But there won't be another resizing array operation
하지만 배열 리사이징 연산은
until it either gets totally full or half again full.
새로운 용량을 기준으로 완전히 꽉 차거나 다시 1/4배가 되지 않는 한 실행되지 않습니다.
So the invariant of that is that the array is always between 25% and
따라서 이 상황에서의 불변성(invariant)은 첫째로 배열이 언제나
100% full, number one.
용량의 25%와 100% 사이 만큼 차있다는 점입니다.
And number two, that every time you resize, you've already paid for
다음으로 리사이징을 할 때마다, 이미 삽입, 삭제에서
it in an amortized sense by inserting, pushing or popping.
그 비용을 이미 지불한 걸로 볼 수 있다는 겁니다.
So here's just what happens to the array for
여기 작은 클라이언트 프로그램 예시에서
our small client example.
배열에 어떤 일이 일어나는지 봅시다.
And you can see at the beginning, it doubles from one to two to four, but
시작할 때 배열이 1, 2, 4로 배증하는 걸 볼 수 있을텐데,
once it gets to four, it stays, once it gets to eight, it stays at that size for
4가 된 뒤에 8이 되고, 그 뒤에는 연산이 몇 번 있음에도
awhile even though there's some operations.
그 크기를 유지함을 알 수 있습니다.
And it doesn't shrink back to four until after there's only two items in there,
그리고선 겨우 2 개 아이템이 남을 때까지 줄어들지 않고 있다가
and then it shrinks, and so forth.
2개 아이템이 남아서야 줄어듭니다.
So array resizing doesn't happen that often, but
배열 리사이징은 그리 자주 발생하진 않지만,
it's a very effective way of implementing the stack API with
배열을 이용해 스택 API를 구현하는 매우 효율적인 방법입니다.
an array where the client does not have to provide the maximum capacity of the stack.
사용자가 스택의 최대 용량을 알려주지 않아도 되니까요.
But still, we're guaranteed that the amount of the memory that we are use
그럼에도 아직도, 매 순간 우리가 사용하고 있는 메모리의 양은
is always only a constant multiple of the number of items actually on the stack.
스택에 있는 아이템의 수의 상수배에 불과함합니다.
So, the analysis now says that the average running time per
이제 여기 나온 분석은 pop과 push의 연산이 어떤 순서로 주어지든
operation for whatever the sequence of operations is,
연산 당 평균 실행 시간이
the average running time is going to be proportional to a constant.
상수에 비례하게 됨을 알려줍니다.
Now, there is a worst case, that is, at the point when the stack doubles,
이 때 최악의 경우는, 스택이 증배할 때이며
it takes time proportional to N.
이 때는 N에 비례하는 시간이 걸립니다.
So it's not quite as good performance as we might like.
이러한 성능은 우리가 바라지 않는 성능이죠.
But the advantage that we get is very fast pushes and
하지만 우리가 얻은 장점은 매우 빠른 push 및 pop 연산이죠.
pops, just access array and increment it, and very efficient for most operations.
그저 배열에 접근해 증가시키기만 할 뿐이니, 대부분의 연산에서는 매우 효율적입니다.
And for many, many clients, that's an effective tradeoff to make.
또한 많은, 많은 사용자에게 해볼 만한, 효과적인 트레이드오프(trade-off)입니다.
So what about memory usage?
그럼 메모리 사용량은 어떨까요?
Well, this is the analysis of memory usage for
여기 스택에 대한 메모리 사용량 분석이 있습니다.
stacks, and it's actually less memory than for strings.
문자열이 사용하는 메모리 공간보단 확실히 작습니다.
The amount used is between 8N and 32N,
8N에서 32N 사이의 양을 사용하는데
depending on how full the array is and
배열이 얼마나 찼느냐에 따라 달라집니다.
just a quick analysis of the amount of space that arrays take in Java.
Java에서 배열이 사용하는 공간 크기를 간단히 분석해봅시다.
So, again, this analysis is just for the stack itself, not for
반복하지만, 이 분석은 스택 그 자체에 대한 것으로,
the strings, which the client owns.
클라이언트 프로그램이 소유한 문자열에 대한 분석은 하지 않았습니다.
So, what are the tradeoffs between using a resizing array versus a linked list?
그럼 리사이징을 지원하는 배열 기반 구현과 연결 리스트 기반 구현 간의 트레이드오프는 뭘까요?
Those are two different implementations of the same API,
같은 API에 대해 다른 구현이고
and the client can use them interchangeably.
사용자는 둘을 교환하여 사용할 수 있습니다.
Which one is better?
어떤 게 낫죠?
In many situations, we're going to have multiple implementations of APIs,
많은 상황에서, 여러 API 구현을 다루게 되겠고
and depending on properties of the client program,
클라이언트 프로그램의 성질에 의존적입니다만
we're going to have to choose which one is the better one to use.
어느 것이 좋은 것인지 골라야만 할 겁니다.
So for linked lists, every operation takes constant time in the worst case,
연결 리스트는 최악의 경우에 상수 시간이 걸립니다.
that's a guarantee.
이는 성능이 (예측이 된다는 점에서) 보장된다는 의미입니다.
But we have to use a little extra time and space to deal with the links.
다만 연결을 처리하기 위한 시간과 공간이 좀 더 필요합니다.
So it's going to be slower.
더 느려질 수 있죠.
Resizing-array implementation.
리사이징이 되는 배열 구현의 경우,
We have a good amortized time, so total averaged over the whole process is good.
좋은 분할상환 시간을 가지므로 전체 과정에서의 평균적인 연산 성능이 좋습니다.
We have less wasted space and probably faster implementation of each operation.
공간 낭비를 덜 하며, 각 연산은 아마 더 빠르게 동작할 겁니다.
And so for some clients, maybe that makes a difference.
몇몇 사용자에게는 이것이 차이를 만듭니다.
Perhaps you wouldn't want to use a resizing-array implementation at
아마 비행기가 착륙하려는 시점에 동작할 프로그램에
the moment that your plane's coming in for a landing.
리사이징을 하는 배열 구현을 사용하진 않을 겁니다.
You wouldn't want it to all of a sudden not implement some operation quickly.
갑자기 일부 연산만 빠르게 동작하지 않길 바라진 않을테니까요.
If you need that kind of order, maybe in an internet switch where packets
비슷한 예로, 아마 패킷(packet)이 빠른 속도(rate)로 들어오는
are coming through at a great rate, you wouldn't want to be in a situation where
인터넷 스위치에서 갑작스럽게 모든 것이 느려져서
you're missing some data because something got slow all of a sudden.
데이터 일부를 손실해서는 안 되는 상황을 생각할 수 있습니다.
So that's a tradeoff that the client can make.
따라서 무슨 구현이 나을지는, 사용할 사용자에게 주어진 트레이드오프입니다.
If I want that guarantee, if I want to be sure that every operation's going to be
성능 보장을 해야 한다면, 즉 모든 연산이 빠르게 동작해야 하면
fast, I'll use a linked list.
저라면 연결 리스트 기반 스택 구현을 쓰겠습니다.
And if I don't need that guarantee, if I just care about the total amount of time,
보장이 필요 없고 다만 전체 시간만 신경이 쓰이는 상황이면
I'll probably use the resizing-array because the total will be much less,
저라면 리사이징이 되는 배열 기반의 스택 구현을 쓰겠습니다. 개별 연산이 빨라서
because individual operations are fast.
전체 시간이 훨씬 줄어들테니까요.
So even with these simple data structures, we have really important
이런 간단한 자료구조에서조차, 많은 실제 상황에서 차이를 만드는
tradeoffs that actually make a difference in lots of practical situations.
정말 중요한 트레이드오프들을 볼 수 있습니다.